<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter from Amsterdam to a friend in Paris</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1439A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43388</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27376633</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27376633</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110092</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48038)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110092)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1725:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter from Amsterdam to a friend in Paris</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:110092:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110092:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A LETTER FROM AMSTERDAM TO A FRIEND IN PARIS.</head>
            <head type="sub">Steriles dominantur auenae.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>S<hi rend="sup">R.</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I never complyed more chearfully with your commands then at preſent, ſince I have the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to diſcharge a debt I owe to the Chriſtian World. You deſire to be ſatisfied concerning this ſo much talked of Plott in England w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> you ſay is the only ſubiect of all Diſcourſes and as it hath alarmed all the King of Great Brittains Kingdomes and Dominions ſo it hath ſtruck with aſtoniſhment the greateſt part of Europe. Iudicious People find them ſelues in great perplexity; on the one ſide they cannot co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend how ſo many Religious Perſons whoſe education hath been in the ſpirit of Meekneſſe &amp; Humility, ſo many men of Quality, who have given ſuch vnqueſtionable Proofs of their Loyalty, and expoſed both Fortunes &amp; lives to maintain the life and Autority of the late &amp; preſent Kings of England, ſo many of all degrees and conditions hitherto reputed honeſt in their Actions and ſincere in their words, ſhould vpon à ſuddaine bee engaged in à Diabolicall and Damnable Conſpiracy to take away the life of the King &amp; ſubvert the Government. On the other ſide, if there bee noe plott how comes à whole Kingdome to be ſo impoſed vpon as to believe it, And then to uſe ſuch ſeverityes and Rigours far different from
<pb facs="tcp:110092:2"/>the vſuall temper of the Nation? This is the Riddle which you deſire to bee ſolved: I ſhall doe it in brief and plainly; for Truth never appears better then in downright and vnartificiall expreſſions. Sr. I can aſſure you there is no ſuch thing as à Plott of the Catholicks; no deſigne againſt his ſacred Majeſtyes Perſon, Government, or Laws of the Land: If any particular Perſon has transgreſſed let him ſuffer for it, <hi>Anima quae peccaverit ipſa morietur.</hi> This is the deſire of all good Chriſtians; and I am credibly informd that the Generall of the Ieſuits, vpon the firſt bruit of this Conſpiracy, ſhould ſay of his Religious, <hi>ſi ſe miſcuerint iſtiuſmodi Rebus, dignum luant ſupplicium.</hi> But as à bare Accuſation without manifeſt proofs is deem'd a mere Calumny, ſo a bare deniall is a ſlender Apology, to take of a prejudicate opinion: I ſhall therefore make it out with vndeniable Reaſons. You have rightly deſcribed the partyes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed; I ſhall decypher the Accuſers and then appeal to your Iudgment whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they bee Perſons that deſerve any Credit.</p>
            <p>Sergeant <hi>Mainard,</hi> in M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Colmans Triall pag. 8. ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Oates was the firſt man that wee heare of, that diſcovered this Treaſon: <q>Hee was the ſingle man, that diſcovered ſo many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Active Agents in ſo great a Treaſon.</q> It is worth the pains to informe you what this Oates is. His Father in his younger dayes was a devoute ſilck weaver, but in the late Rebellion found it more for his advantage to turn an Anabaptiſticall Preacher, After the Returne of his Majeſty, hee became a Miniſter and was beneficed in or near Haſtings, at preſent he is an old fornicator in Kingſtreet ſouthampton Buildings. He trained vp his ſon Titus to the Pulpit, and having him ſelfe procured a better living reſigned that to his ſon; but whether he was baptized or no is a great queſtion; though the ſon ſaith he was chriſtened at ſeventeen yeares of Age, yet I preſume it was done after the Anabaptiſticall forme. His debaucheries are notoriouſly knowne in and about Haſtings; I ſhall not defile my paper with them: yet I muſt not omitt to tell you how hee accuſed an Innocent man of Sodomie, but was convicted of Perjury (The Conviction ſtands vpon Record) and was clapt in Priſon, but hee brake it. Sometime After hee was embarcked for Tangers, hee fell to his old Tricks of Sodomy in the ſhip and was taken <hi>in flagranti,</hi> to eſcape hanging, according to his demerit, he adventured drowning and ſtole away narrowly to ſhore in the Cockboat: But this, you will ſay, is not to the purpoſe; his Majeſties Indulgence has granted him a plenarie impunitie; &amp; his infamous life does not de grade him from a capacity, to bear wittneſſe for the King; nay his Patrons allow this, and like him the better; the more wicked he is, the fitter inſtrument to make diſcoveries of wicked deſignes: for who more proper <hi>to vnkennell a Fox
<pb facs="tcp:110092:2"/>then the Terrier, that is part of him?</hi> And as to his legall conviction of Perjury recorded <hi>In perpetuam rei memoriam,</hi> tho it diſables him from making a Legall Teſtimony, yet it implyes only a Preſumption, <hi>ſemel malus ſemper praeſumitur malus;</hi> And not a neceſſity of allwayes lying from that time forward; and who can Tell but heemay ſpeake truth at preſent! be it ſo; yet it muſt bee granted that the Infamy of the Accuſer takes of from his Credit with the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious, and obligeth a conſciencious Perſon to waue his Iudgment, untill better proofs bee produced; as all ſo that every one muſt bee looked vpon as Innocent by the eye of the Law, if there bee no allegation againſt him, beſides the teſtimony of a Perſon perjured vpon Record. Iuſtice then and Charity (That is the law of God and man) maintaine a man in poſſeſſion of his Innocency, vntill he is either outed by the evidence of his owne Acts, or ejected by a Legall formality. This Argument muſt bee allowed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude thus far; and I pretend no more. This you ſay is too general, and not to your entire ſatiſfaction; J will therefore deſcend to the particulars of the Accuſation, and make out with evidence that they are groundleſſe and falſe.</p>
            <p>On ſonday 29. September 1678. ſtil: v. his Majeſtye being preſent in Councell, Titus Oates depoſed vpon oath, how hee had been employed by the Ieſuits to Treat with Don Iohn of Auſtria. and that hee did actually treat with him at Madrid about this Conſpiracy; and mentioned ſeverall other paſſages happened at Madrid. Hee repeats alſo his benig at Madrid Iuly 77. in his depoſitions taken by order of the houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>How wel he knew Don Iohn, may be ſeen by the deſcription hee made of his Perſon to his Majeſty and Councell, I report myſelfe to thoſe that were preſent; That he never was at Madrid is thus made out; Hee was not acquainted with the Ieſuits before April 1677. This he cannot deny. His great friend and acquaintance that firſt introduced him can teſtifie as much. Towards the end of April hee was on ſhipboard in the downs, as apears by his letter dated there. As to his arrivall in ſpaine his ſtay there and returne for England I ſhall give you the Depoſitions of ſeverall Perſons vpon oath before a publick Notary.</p>
            <p>Don Duarte ſal, Michael Hore, and Iohn Grace Merchants of Bilbao depoſed how they knew very wel Titus Ambroſius alias Oats an Engiſhman, that hee landed at Bilbao on the 16. of May 1677. ſtilonovo brought from London in the ſhip called the Merchant of Biſcay Lucas Roach Maſter; hee ſtayd there 10. dayes or there abouts; And thence went the neareſt way to vagliadolid with Martin Lornitz Eſpinoſa a Guide to the Colledge of Saint Albans; where hee continued as they vnderſtood, vntil hee ſet out back for
<pb facs="tcp:110092:3"/>Bilbao; he arrived here the 3. of November following; hee ſtayd in towne about 8. dayes and was ſhipd vpon the Marchant of Bilbao bound for Top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam in England. Martin de Lornitz Eſpinoſa a guide dwelling at Bilbao de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vpon oath before a Notary that hee knew Titus Ambroſius as having conducted him on a Mule the right way from Bilbao to the Coledge of S. Alban in vagliadolid where they arrived on the beginning of June 1677. Moreover that hee is aſcertaind how the ſaid Titus was never 5. leagues out of vagliadolid vntill he returned for Bilbao for having occaſion to travel fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that way (as being a Guide much employed becauſe he knew the french Language) as often as he paſt he found him at vagliadolid. The fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid depoſitions were taken on the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Ianuarie 1679. ſtilo novo at Bilbao before Iohn Baptiſta de Aſturiaca a publick notary: the originals are kept at S. Omers together with an Authentical Atteſtation that the ſaid Iohn Baptiſta is the Kings publick Notary.</p>
            <p>That he went not to Madrid from the time of his arrival at the Colledge of S. Albans in vagliadolid vntil his departure from the Colledge is made out by the depoſitions vpon oath of F. Manuel de Calatajud Rector and F. Domingo Rames Procurator of the ſaid Colledge as followeth: Titus Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſius alias Oats departed from the Colledge of S. Albans in vagliadolid for Bilbao on ſaturday 30. October 1677. he entered vpon the iſt of Iune about 4. or 5. in the afternoone in to the Colledge; from the time of his entrance til the day of his expulſion he never lay one night out of the Colledge which alſo appears, by the Books.</p>
            <p>That he went not to Madrid from the Day of his departure from the ſaid Colledge vntill his arrival at Bilbao vpon returne, is made out by the Depoſitions of Iohn de Sandoval the Guide who furniſhed him with a Mule and accompanied him from vagliadolid to Bilbao: as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <q>On ſaturday the 30. October 1677. we departed from the Colledge of vagliodolid and lodged that night at Torquemada ten leagues of; the next morning I told him I would heare Maſſe hee ſaid he would not heare. The next night we lodged at Burgos, and the morning after being the Feaſt of all ſaints wee both heard Maſſe at the Dominicans, then wee kept on our Iourney, and at noone arrived at a place cald the White Inne having broke faſt in the morning; he inquired of the hoſt whether hee might ſay Maſſ in the Chappel over the way, I asked him how hee could ſay maſſ having broke his faſt in the morning. Hee anſwered that's no great matter, I have ſeveral times ſaid 3. or 4. Maſſes after breakfaſt. On the third of November about noone wee arrived at Bilbao.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:110092:3"/>
            <p>The ſaid depoſitions were made before Joſeph Morales at vagliadolid the Kings publick Notary on the 20. of December 1678. The Originals with all the uſual Formalities in ſuch caſes are kept at S. Omers.</p>
            <p>How after his arrival at Bilbao he never went out of the towne before he was ſhipt for England is atteſted by Mr. Michael Hore Marchant of Bilbao.</p>
            <p>Titus Ambroſius alias Oates arrived here with the Caſtilian Guide, who returned homewards the next day.</p>
            <p>Titus ſtayed here about 8. or 10. dayes during w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> time hee never went from Bilbao but kept Company with the Engliſh in Towne vntil he was ſhipt for England, which was in the Katch cald the <hi>Bilbao Merchant Thomas Richard Maſter,</hi> bound for Exon, to which place I vnderſtood the veſſell belongs. I hope this fully ſatisfies you that Oates was not at Madrid and therefore that he is perjured as to this point. Titus Oates being expell'd out of the Colledge of Vagliadolid with a very bad caracter which will ſhortly be publiſhed in a larger treatiſe, &amp; departed out of ſpaine came to London in November 1677. And before the end of the ſame moneth prevailed with the Jeſuits to bee ſent over to S. Omers. He departed November 26. ſti: v: on a munday from London in a coach to Dover and arrived at S. Omers 10. of December ſt: no. Now he depoſed vpon Oath at the Kings bench Bar Colemans Triall pag: 18. How he brought a packet of Letters From Mr. Coleman delivered to him by Fenwick at London, <hi>which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I opened when I came to S. Omers.</hi> And ſome few lines after being asked by the Chief Iuſtice. Did <hi>you break it open?</hi> Oates. <hi>I was at the opening of it and ſaw it and read it.</hi> But this is a peccadillio not worth an animadverſion. What is material, is, that in the Packet there was a letter of thanks to Father Lecheſe for the 10000. pounds given for the propagation of the Catholick Religion and it ſhould be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for no other intent, but for that for which it was ſent; which was to cut of the King of England. pag. 19. Oates ſaith, <hi>I delivered this letter to Father Lecheſe his owne hand.</hi> pag. 20. he ſpoke Latin to P. Lecheſe, which Lecheſe <hi>ſends an Anſwer to this Letter. I brought it to Saint Omers and there it was encloſed in a letter from the Society to Coleman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jt is not worth an obſervation that Oates ſpoke latin; an Jgnorant Dolt that could not ſpeak ſix words nor write 3. lines of true latin; I muſt tell you the Character the ſpaniards <hi>gave of him: wee have a mean opinion of the Engliſh Hereticks ſince ſo ignorant and ridiculous an animal could gain eſteem amongſt them.</hi> This Letter mentioned in Col: Trial contained Treaſon of the higheſt degree. Oates received it at London from Fenwick, brought it to S. Omers where hee was preſent at the opening and reading; he delivered it to Lecheſe his owne
<pb facs="tcp:110092:4"/>hands and brought back his Anſwer to S. Omers. ſo that Oates after his arrival at S. Omers muſt have gone to Paris to deliver the Letter, and then returnd back to S. Omer. But from his arrival at S. Omers which was the tenth day of December ſt: n: til the 23. of Iune ſt: no: on which day he departed for good and all hee never lay out of S. Omers but one or two nights at Watten the Ieſuits Noviſhip 2. leagues diſtant; this is depoſed vpon Oath by 20. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before the Eſchevins of the place, and an Authentical Teſtimony is extant of it. Are you ſatisfied now that Oates is perjured in another material point relating to this pretended conſpiracy? I come now to the maine body of the Plott. Colemans Trial pag. 21. Mr. Oates ſpeaks: <q>
                  <hi>In the moneth of Aplil</hi> ſt: ve: in the moneth of may no: ſti: there was a Conſult held at London, it was begun at the white Horſe Tauern, after they had conſulted to ſend a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curator to Rome they adjourn'd themſelves to ſeueral clubs and meetings. They went on to theſe Reſolves, that Pickering and Groves ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in attempting to aſſaſſinate the kings Perſon; Groves was to have 1500.l. Pikering 30000. Maſſes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Colemans Triall pag: 27. <hi>In the moneth of may laſt new</hi> ſtile April old ſtile. <q>I think within a day after our Conſult I was at Mr Langhornes Chamber: He had ſeveral Commiſſions which he cald Patents; Amongſt his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions I ſaw one from the General of the Society of Ieſus by vertue of <hi>a brief from the Pope by which hee was enabled,</hi> for Coleman to be Secretary of ſtate.</q> Iuſtice Wilde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What other Commiſſions were there in Mr. Langhornes Chamber?</hi> Oats <hi>Agreat many I cannot remember all there was a Commiſſion for my Lord Arundel of Warder The Lord Powis and ſeveral others.</hi> Lord chief-Iuſtice. Ibid. p. 28. <hi>When did you ſee the Commiſſions?</hi> Oates. <hi>In the moneth of April old ſtile May new ſtile.</hi> Lordchief Iuſtice: <hi>What time did you come over from S. Omers?</hi> Oates. <hi>In the moneth of April. Ibid. pag.</hi> 29. Oates ſpeaks, <hi>Mr Langhorne I hear you have received the Commiſſions from Rome; He ſaid, hee had: ſhall I have the honour to ſee ſome of them; He ſaid I might: hee thought hee might truſt mee, and ſo hee might for that very day I gave him an account of the Conſult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moſt of the ſaid particulars are mentioned likewiſe in Oates his depoſitions taken by order of the houſe of Commons. As the ſeveral Conſults held at Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don in April and May at which he was preſent about aſſaſſinating the Kings Perſon The Commiſſions of Military and Civil Offices, as alſo for the Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricks, ſeen by him in Mr Langhornes Chamber Theſe are the two main branches of the Plott: <hi>Deſtroying the King Perſon and ſubverting the Covernment.</hi> How abſurde and ridiculous this Fable is to a man of indifferent Capacity I leave to your Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, J have not leaſure to make gloſſes. I muſt tell you in one word Oates came to S. Omers on y 10. December ſtilo novo 1677. and ſtayed there
<pb facs="tcp:110092:4"/>vntill 23. Iune 78. ſtilo novo all that Time hee never lay out of the Colledge but one or 2. nights at a place two leagues diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, there is an Authentical inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon that ſubject made by the Eſchevins of the place, having examined 20. witteneſſes vpon Oath for that Purpoſe There are a hundred more ready to teſtifie it in the ſame manner. How was Oates then at London preſent at the foreſaid Conſults, and ſaw the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions in a Chamber of the Inner Temple in April or May? Are you ſatisfied that hee is perjured? He ſwore that hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion to Sr. Francis Ratcliff in Wilde garden the ſummer 1678. where as it was made out that Sr. Francis had not been in London within four yeares. Hee ſwore that Pierſon my Lord Powis his Secretary in the month of Iune 78. receiued a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion for his Lord in Wilde ſtreet, and brought there in a Coach 300.l. in exchange for it, where as it can be proved by 500. witt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes that Mr Pierſon was not in London nor within 80. miles of it from Aug: 9. 1677. vntil October the 5. 1678. Hee ſwore that one Preſton a married man of many years was a Prieſt, and how hee had been ſeveral times at Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion with him: the Contrary was proved to his Face. My Lord Chanceller can Authenticate it. Hee ſwore before the Lords that hee could accuſe no other member of their houſe nor any Perſon of Conſideration out of their houſe; yet within few dayes after hee ſwore in the ſame place that the Queen was deeply engaged in the Plot, my Lord Salisbury will Iuſtifie it, who cauſed the Iournal to be inſpected, and asked the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the houſe whether the Queen was a Perſon of Conſideration or no? I ſhould alleadge his falſe accuſations of Mr. Ireland for words and Actions done and ſpoke at London when it is depoſed by many Honorable and worthy Perſons that he was far diſtant from the place, which ſhall bee made out with euidence in a treatiſe a part. All the other particulars are canvaſſed and found falſe in the ſame degree ſo that Oats had great reaſon to ſay <hi>Colemans</hi> Trial 30. pag. <hi>Priſoners may ſupplant Evidence when they know it and bring Perſons to ſuch circumſtances as time and Place.</hi> J hope you are fully ſatisfied that the Plott is a Diabolicall Fiction of this Oates: that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is a pure compound of Lyes forgeries and Perjuryes. J hear there is a ſtatue preparing for him as preſerver of the Kingdom. I ſhall adorne it with an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphe for his ſake.</p>
            <p>Vpon this fellows Teſtimony is grounded the whole Machin of the Plott, others are brought in as buttereſſes to ſupport a weak foundation. Vpon his ſingle teſtimony the Lords and many Gentlemen of Quality and fortune beſides Prieſts and diuers others are committed to Priſon and ſome of them, moſt barbarouſly treated. Catholiks houſes are ſearcht in all parts for arms and Prieſts; All Catholiks in leſſe then ſeven dayes warning are baniſht out of London
<pb facs="tcp:110092:5"/>and Ten miles about. Others in the Country confined within five miles of their habitation; ſo many forced to take Oaths againſt their Conſcience. The train bande vp in London, watch and ward thorough all the Kingdom. Many ſevere Bills prepared in Parliament againſt poor Papiſts. An vniuerſal conſternation in all places. And what is beyond all admiration both houſes of Parliament vote that there is a plott.</p>
            <p>Others I ſay are brought as Buttr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſes. In the firſt place comes in a ſecond to Oates, a knight of the Poſt ready to ſweare what you pleaſe, one Bedloe a Fidlers ſon. Its hard to give a Character of him in a ſhort letter, he is wel known over moſt parts of England, Low countreyes France and Spaine for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries cheats, Robberyes and Rogueries: Guzman and the engliſh Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue were meere novices to him; but it is no marvell for J am credibly informed by a Perſon of worth that hee carries a familiar devil about, which he cals his Patrimony, and if he were well ſearcht it might be found. Hee hath diſgraced many honorable names in his Travells as Lord Cornwallis in France, and Lord Gerard (not him of Gerards Bromley) in Spaine, but all theſe are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable crimes. Hee cheated even his owne Friend Titus Oates alias Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius in Vagliadolid, yet Oates has ſworn that hee never ſaw Bedloe before: and brings it as a great proof of the truth that his Depoſitions ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by a meere ſtranger. I have in my Cuſtody to atteſt it Titus his owne Letter dated at Vagliadolid September. 3. 77. to Mr. Grace a Marchant. <q>I am ſorry for Mr. Franklin's misfortune by the pretended Lord Gerard, hee ſhould firſt have demanded of the ſaid Lord three things, his Patent of honour, his licence vnder the great ſeal of England to travel, and Letters of Credit for his Reception. If the ſaid perſon were my Lord Gerard, I aſſure you that hee's an errant Rogue and is outlawed in England for a murder com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vpon a boy whoſe neck he broke Villanouſly &amp; baſely; Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are out againſt him. His complice was tried for his life but was quitted, the fault lying on the ſaid Lord Gerard as the ſole Murderer: I have written againſt him to the Iriſh Archbiſhop and Father ſweetmans a Jeſuit that they may not countenance him, he ſtole ten peices of 8. out of my Drawer being left alone in my Chamber, whilſt J went to provide him ſomewhat to eat and <hi>drink.</hi>
               </q> This is Oates his owne Letter, I am not bound to correct ſome miſtake that lyes in it. Eſquire Brandon Gerard is much obliged to Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loe, and has expreſſed his Gratitude at a dead lift. When his Majeſty with great indignation had refuſed to ſigne Bedloes pardon extended to a certain day, who more concerned in the Caſe then the Eſquire? who more importune to preſſ him too it, then hee, and at laſt effected it? for your aſſurance that
<pb facs="tcp:110092:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>this Bedloe was the counterfeit Gerard I ſend you a copy of a letter from Mr. Hore Marchant of Bilbao to a friend at Madrid. December 12. 1678. The Originall J have in my cuſtody.</p>
            <p>
               <q>El Diabolico Titus (Oates) may bee proved a perjurer if hee ſwore that hee was at Madrid I writ a couple of lines to a friend in London to whom I ſent the note Titus gave mee for the 10. pieces of 8. J lent him; and by the way gave him to vnderſtand that one Williams of whom his letter to Mr. Grace makes mention, has preſented himſelfe Before the Parliament, declaring himſelfe to have had a hand in Sr. Edmunbury Godfreys death. I know the ſaid Williams to bee a knave and a highway Robber, and Titus Oates told me that hee had ſtolen from him at Vagliadolid ten peices of 8. This Williams was here with his brother, the one pretended himſelfe to bee the young Lord Gerard. and the other his Tutor, The one is a ſhoemaker the other a Carpenter: they have vſed many cheats and other mad pranks amongſt our Marchants.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This fellow is quallified to bee a Witneſſe in the caſe, hee hath obtained an vniverſal pardon vnder the great ſeal; but noe act of Grace nor oblivion can cancell the memory of his miſdemeanours. This man hath far more wit and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence then Oates tho hee is only ſecond and not principal in the Intrigue. He and Oates ſwore ſtoutly againſt Mr. Colema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who took it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before and after ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and at the Gallows, that he had never ſeen Oates before hee was brought into trouble, nor Bedloe before the day of his Triall.</p>
            <p>A third Perſon brought on the ſtage is one Prans a ſilver ſmith, who hath ſworn forward and backward ſeveral times in the Caſe: hee is now for the Plot, but I preſume when the next fit comes he will ſwear againſt it.</p>
            <p>Stephen Dugdale born of mean Parents in Darbyſhire after ſome him ſpent in ſchoole was applyed to the plow, but being fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to have skill in Arithmeticke, and a capacity for a better employment, he was entertain'd by the Lord Aſhto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for bailey. After ſome years ſpent in that ſervice honeſtly as is ſuppoſed, hee turned ſpendthrift by frequenting foot races, making matches abetting and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing often ſuch conſiderable ſomms as once of three hundred pound, that to maintaine his Credit he vſed to imbezel his Lords money and play ſeveral other cheats, things wel known and talked of in the neighbourhood before they were diſcovered by his Lord in October laſt, which was on this occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Hee had told his Lord that certain Tenants had not payed their Rent whereof one coming in the way was asked the Reaſon, who anſwered that is was payed long before; the Lord asked his Bailey: whether it were true, hee ſtoode vpon the denial very confidently, vntill the Tenant was brought in place. Then hee fell vpon his
<pb facs="tcp:110092:6"/>knees begd his Lordſhips pardon promiſing future amendment if hee might keep his ſervice, which was granted at the interceſſion of a Gentleman then in the houſe, provided hee would procure out of hand the money for which hee had ſold two yoke of Oxen: this hee vndertook to doe and aſſured his Lord that within few dayes the buyer would bring it, but noe money Coming hee was asked who the buyer was; hee ſaid one of Newcaſtle, and how a certain man of Stafford was wittneſſe to the bargain. The Lord found vpon enquiry at Stafford how the price of his Oxen had bin diſpoſed of to pay a debt of his Baily. About the ſame time he ſold of certain Runts unknown to his Lord, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d kept the money. For theſe and many other cheating tricks notoriouſly known in the familie and Countrey about Tixall, hee was turned out of ſervice. Towards the end of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember he was committed to the Jaile of Stafford, where hee took the Oaths, but being asked by two Iuſtices of Peace whether hee knew any thing of the Plot. hee anſwered that hee knew nothing. Yet on the 23. December, having had notice of 200.l. and other adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tages that were promiſed to any one that would make further diſcovery of the Plot, being now in a deſper ate condition and never like to get out of Priſon by reaſon of his debts, layed hold on the proffer and feyned a falſe accuſation. You ſee vpon what account he is brought in ſhortly wee expect to have his depoſitions publiſhed.</p>
            <p>I hope this ſhort account wil ſatisfie you that there is noe plot; I have made vſe of one Topick only to defeat Oates his depoſition, to wit, by making out that he and the Partyes accuſed were far aſunder at ſuch times as he fixes the Treaſon to, which he laid to their charge.</p>
            <p>Your ſelfe will reflect vpon the Abſurdityes and Improbabilityes in the whole ſubject of his depoſition. As that Oates was a Ieſuit, a fellow unknown ſhould be entruſted with ſecrets of moſt dangerous conſequence, and then turn'd away diſgracefully to betray them. To be cal'd by a particular Patent to conſults, to bee empowered to open letters. That 40000. black Bills ſhould be provided, and yet be in viſible. That a Generall of a Religious Order ſhould bee empowered to diſpoſe of all Offices Military and Civil in the Kingdom by comiſſions. That ſuch honourable Perſons of Eſtates and diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould bee ſo ſimple as to believe it, and ſtake both life and Fortune on ſuch a mad caſt, &amp;c. All the whole Contrivance is a meer midſommer nights dreame.</p>
            <p>But all this increaſes the difficulty of the ſecond Quere, how the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could be worked to ſuch a temper as to belive it. This is ſoone answered if the time were ſeaſonable: the ſucceſſe of a plot doth not ſo much depend vpon the Compoſition as vpon the management; There lyes all the art and wit. <hi>Verbum ſapienti ſatis.</hi> Adieu.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110092:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
